Guide to the Paul Kagan Utopian Communities Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Paul Kagan's Writings, 1970-1976; Series V; 1.0' (3 boxes)
  - NEW WORLD UTOPIAS
    - Correspondence
      - "A" general, 1972-74 (Box 35, Folder 607)
        - Forgostein, Harold, 1973 (Box 35, Folder 613)
        - "G-H" general, 1972-74 (Box 35, Folder 614)
        - Harris, Iverson L., 1971-75 (Box 35, Folder 615)
        - Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, 1971-74 (Box 35, Folder 616)
        - "J-K" general, 1973-74 (Box 35, Folder 617)
        - "L" general, 1971-75 (Box 35, Folder 618)
        - "M" general, 1973-74 (Box 35, Folder 619)
        - "N-P" general, 1972-74 (Box 35, Folder 620)
        - Penguin Books, 1973-75 (Box 35, Folder 621)
        - "R" general, 1971-74 (Box 35, Folder 622)
        - "S" general, 1971-75 (Box 35, Folder 623)
        - "T" general, 1971, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 624)
        - "U" general, 1971-74 (Box 35, Folder 625)
        - "V-Z" general, 1971-74 (Box 35, Folder 626)
        - Unidentified, 1971-73 (Box 35, Folder 627)
    - Documents
      - Memorandum of Agreement between Kagan and Penguin Books, 1973 Aug 24 (Box 35, Folder 628)
      - Drafts of agreement between Richard Rose and Paul Kagan, 1973, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 629)
      - Memorandum of Agreement. Blank form of the California Historical Society (Box 35, Folder 630)
      - Receipts for photograph permissions, 1973-75 (Box 35, Folder 631)
      - Receipts for photography work by others, 1974, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 632)
      - Travel receipts, 1971 (Box 35, Folder 633)
      - Call slips, 1971-74 (Box 35, Folder 634)
    - Chapter Drafts
      - "Utopia in the Nineteenth Century," typescript photocopy, corrected, [1972 Jun 13] (Box 35, Folder 635)
      - "Fountain Grove," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 636)
      - "Icaria Speranza," typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 637)
      - "Theosophists in California," typescript and typescript carbons and photocopies, all corrected (Box 35, Folder 638-642)
      - Kaweah, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 643)
      - "Holy City," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 35, Folder 644)
      - "Pisgah Grande," typescript and typescript carbon, corrected (Box 35, Folder 645)
      - "Tassajara Zen Mountain Center," typescript, corrected, and typescript photocopy (Box 35, Folder 646)
      - Conclusion, "Chapter XI. Perspectives" typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 647)
      - Conclusion, "Chapter Nine. What Does the Commune Mean?" typescript photocopy, corrected, [1972 Jun 13] (Box 36, Folder 648)
      - Conclusion, "Chapter 10. The Search for Community" typescript and typescript photocopy, corrected (Box 36, Folder 649)
      - Conclusion, "Chapter 10. Conclusion" typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 650)
      - Conclusion - captions for photographs, typescript, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 651)
      - Bibliography page proof, typescript photocopy, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 652)
      - Layout proof, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 653)
      - Setting typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 654-655)
      - Sample page proofs, n.d.
        See: Oversize, box 44, folder 794
    - Photographs
      - Copy prints of buildings, people and printed material for chapter one (Box 36, Folder 656)
      - Views of New World Utopias exhibition, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 657)
    - Notes
      - Descriptive Notes Assembled for New World Utopias, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 658)
      - General background notes (Box 36, Folder 659-660)
      - List of photographs in New World Utopias, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 661)
      - Lists of sources for photographs, n.d. (Box 36, Folder 662)
      - List of books in the Utopia Reading Room [?] and at Huntington Library (Box 36, Folder 663)
    - Printed Material
      - New World Utopias: A Photographic Search for Community. Penguin Books, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 664)
      - Photocopies of articles providing a general background to history of communes/utopias in United States (Box 37, Folder 665)
      - Reviews, 1975, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 666)
        See also: Oversize, box 44, folder 795
      - Printed illustrations for chapter one, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 667)
      - Clippings, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 668)
    - Visual Material
      - Poster advertisement for New World Utopias, [1975]
        See: Oversize, box 39, folder 716
      - Poster advertisement for exhibition at The Oakland Museum, Aug 9-Sept 28, 1975
        See: Broadside cabinet, folder 834
    - Other Papers
      - Penguin Books, Inc. author's questionnaire, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 669)
      - Two pages of article by Bob [Robert Hine] sent to Kagan for review, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 670)
      - Captions for exhibition, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 671)
      - Syllabi for classes on utopias and communitarian settlements (photocopies) (Box 37, Folder 672)
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - "A California Utopia: Llano del Rio"
      - Layout sheets (photocopies), n.d. (Box 37, Folder 673)
    - "In Search of a New Community"
      - Page proof, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 674)
      - Photocopy of printed version, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 675)
    - Introduction to "Ozymandias"
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 676)
    - "Outside the Mainstream"
      - Correspondence, 1975-76 (Box 37, Folder 677)
      - Drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript photocopies (Box 37, Folder 678)
      - Photographs of buildings and people (Box 37, Folder 679)
      - Notes, 1976, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 680)
      - Photocopy of page proof, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 681)
      - Offprint, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 682)
      - Photocopies of Zen Center pamphlets and leaflets (Box 37, Folder 683)
    - Unidentified Material
      - Outline and table of contents to unidentified works (Box 37, Folder 684)
      - Photograph of unidentified man in a chair, n.d. (Box 37, Folder 685)
      - Cover of "Maitreya" with Kagan's photograph of William Riker's house, mounted, n.d.
        See: Oversize, box 44, folder 796
- Oversize, 14.0' (10 boxes)
  Oversize contains oversize material from series I-V, and is listed in box order.
  - Correspondence: A. H. Moore and "Friends of Llano" (in Series I), 1947 Jun-Jul (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 686)
  - Gateway to Freedom: Early drafts, typescript, corrected (in Series I), n.d. (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 687)
  - Gateway to Freedom: Introduction: later draft, typescript and mimeograph, corrected (in Series I) (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 688)
  - Alice Constance Austin. Architectural drawing (in Series I), n.d. (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 689)
  - Buck, H. L. "Just a Correction" broadside (in Series I), n.d. (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 690)
  - Industrial Democrat Leesville, Louisiana (in Series I), 1935 Jun-Oct (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 691-692)
  - Map of the Llano Cooperative Colony (in Series I), n.d. (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 693)
  - "A Life Time of Trial and Error," typescript, corrected (in Series I) (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 694)
  - The Call New York, New York (in Series I), 1943-44 (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 695-697)
  - Common Sense (in Series I), 1954 May, Jun (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 698)
  - Friday New York, New York (in Series I) (Box 38 (Oversize), Folder 699-700)
  - Friday New York, New York (in Series I), 1941 (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 701-702)
  - Life Science Hollywood, Calif. (in Series I), 1966 Jan-Feb (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 703)
  - Broadsheet about communism (in Series I) (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 704)
  - Pamphlet: Herbert C. Holdridge (in Series I), 1951 (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 705)
  - Pamphlet: Korean War (in Series I), 1953 (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 706)
  - Pamphlet: Music (in Series I), n.d. (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 707)
  - U. S. Farm News Des Moines, Iowa (in Series I), 1965 Jan (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 708)
  - West Coast Sailors San Francisco (in Series I), 1948 Jun 11 (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 709)
  - Other miscellaneous pamphlets, ephemera and newspapers gathered by Millsap (in Series I), 1948 Aug 1 (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 710)
  - Posters (2) advertising P.C.D.W. doctrine (in Series II), n.d. (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 711-712)
  - Broadsheets published by The Book Publishing Company at The Farm (in Series IV), 1975, n.d. (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 713)
  - Photocopies of correspondence, documents and clippings [from the Bancroft Library?] (in Series IV) (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 714)
  - Master mason's diploma for Betty S. Robertson (in Series IV), 1929 Feb 14 (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 715)
  - Poster advertisement for New World Utopias (in Series V), [1975] (Box 39 (Oversize), Folder 716)
  - Writings and paste-ups for Holy City newsletters, with holograph drafts, drawings, and some illustrations colored in with crayon (in Series II) (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 717)
  - Sign: "P.C.D.W. School of Mastery" (in Series II), n.d. (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 718)
  - Sign advertising Perfect Christian Divine Way doctrine (in Series II) (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 719)
  - Plan-O-Graphic printing plates for newsletters (in Series II), n.d. (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 720)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets and newsletters gathered by William Riker (in Series II) (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 721)
  - Photographs of William and Lucille Riker and others (in Series II) (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 722-729)
  - Drawings of William Riker (in Series II) (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 730-731)
  - Calendar, "Compliments of the Season" by Varian & Harrison, Halcyon, Calif. for 1936 (in Series III), [1935] (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 732)
  - The Electro-Medical News Vol. 1, No. 2. Halcyon, California (in Series III), n.d. (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 733)
  - Photographs: people and buildings (in Series III) (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 734)
  - Fountaingrove people, buildings and landscapes (in Series IV), [1910], n.d. (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 735-737)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Fountaingrove (in Series IV), 1970 (Box 40 (Oversize), Folder 738-741)
  - Banners (18) with inspirational sayings (in Series II), n.d. (Box 41 (Oversize), Folder 742-759)
  - Watercolor poster advertising P.C.D.W. doctrine (in Series II), n.d. (Box 41 (Oversize), Folder 760)
  - Plywood sign advertising the New World Plan (in Series II), n.d. (Box 42 (Oversize), Folder 761)
  - Fountaingrove album containing portraits (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 43 (Oversize), Folder 762)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Halcyon buildings and landscapes (in Series IV), 1970, n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 763-764)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Holy City buildings (in Series IV), 1970 (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 765-768)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Icaria Speranza buildings (in Series IV), 1970 (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 769-772)
  - The Universal Voice Vol IV, Nos. 1, 6, 10; Vol. V, Nos. 3-4 (in Series IV), 1972 Jan-Jun (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 773)
  - Paul Kagan's photographs of Kaweah buildings (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 774)
  - Krotona and Ojai: Portraits by Witzel, Los Angeles; W. Schrempf, Hollywood, Cal. (in Series IV) (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 775)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Ojai (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 776)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Llano del Rio people and buildings (in Series IV) (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 777-779)
  - Copy print of Llano printed material (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 780)
  - Paul Kagan's views of Pisgah buildings (in Series IV), 1970, n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 781-785)
  - Paul Kagan's view of a Point Loma building (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 786)
  - Bruck, Connie, "Too Outrageous for Point Loma," Reader (in Series IV), 1973 Jul-Aug (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 787)
  - Vonnegut, Kurt, Jr. "The Mysterious Madame Blavatsky" McCall's (in Series IV) (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 788)
  - Right On By the Christian World Liberation Front, Berkeley, California (in Series IV), 1970-71 (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 789)
  - The Humanist Friend Hollywood, California (in Series IV), 1940 Nov (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 790)
  - Resource One San Francisco (in Series IV), 1974 Apr (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 791)
  - The Storefront Classroom San Francisco. Vol. 2, Issues 3, 5. Vol. 3, Issues 1, 3. (in Series IV), 1974-75 (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 792)
  - Voyages of Discovery. A Unique 4-Day Seminar with Elizabeth Clare Prophet... Head of the 20,000-member Summit Lighthouse Activity. Broadside (in Series IV), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 793)
  - Sample page proofs (in Series V), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 794)
  - Review in Berkeley Barb (in Series V), 1975 May 9-15 (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 795)
  - Cover of "Maitreya" with Kagan's photograph of William Riker's house, mounted (in Series V), n.d. (Box 44 (Oversize), Folder 796)
  - Album of Krotona, part one (in Series IV) (Box 45 (Oversize), Folder 797-811)
  - Album of Krotona, part two (in Series IV) (Box 46 (Oversize), Folder 812-824)
  - The Imperial Family Bible, Containing the Old and New Testaments. Glasgow: Blackie and Son, Queen Street (in Series IV) (Box 47 (Oversize), Folder 825)
  - "A Life Time of Trial and Error," typescript, corrected (in Series I) (Box bsd, folder 826)
  - Broadside about the House Un-American Activities Committee (in Series I), [1963] (Box bsd, folder 827)
  - Other miscellaneous pamphlets, ephemera and newspapers gathered by Millsap (in Series I) (Box bsd, folder 828)
  - Poster in crayon "Gentile, Jew, To Control, Use and Beautify the Earth and the Fullness Thereof" (in Series II) (Box bsd, folder 829)
  - Strategic plan chart (in Series IV), [1966] (Box bsd, folder 830)
  - Broadside from the Lama Foundation (in Series IV), [1969-70] (Box bsd, folder 831)
  - Broadside from the Lama Foundation (in Series IV), [1969-70] (Box bsd, folder 832)
  - Broadside from the Lama Foundation (in Series IV), [1969-70] (Box bsd, folder 833)
  - Poster advertisement for exhibition at The Oakland Museum, Aug 9-Sept 28, 1975 (in Series V) (Box bsd, folder 834)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 4.0' (8 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 1 (Box 48, Folder 835)
  - Box 1, folder 2 (Box 48, Folder 836)
  - Box 1, folder 3 (Box 48, Folder 837)
  - Box 1, folder 4 (Box 48, Folder 838)
  - Box 1, folder 6 (Box 48, Folder 839)
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 48, Folder 840)
  - Box 1, folder 10 (Box 48, Folder 841)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 48, Folder 842)
  - Box 1, folder 20 (Box 48, Folder 843)
  - Box 1, folder 21 (Box 48, Folder 844)
  - Box 1, folder 27 (Box 48, Folder 845)
  - Box 1, folder 28 (Box 48, Folder 846)
  - Box 1, folder 29 (Box 48, Folder 847)
  - Box 2, folder 48 (Box 48, Folder 848)
  - Box 2, folder 51 (Box 48, Folder 849)
  - Box 2, folder 63 (Box 48, Folder 850)
  - Box 2, folder 77 (Box 48, Folder 851)
  - Box 6, folder 118 (Box 48, Folder 852)
  - Box 6, folder 125 (Box 48, Folder 853)
  - Box 6, folder 132 (Box 48, Folder 854)
  - Box 6, folder 133 (Box 48, Folder 855)
  - Box 6, folder 135 (Box 48, Folder 856)
  - Box 6, folder 136 (Box 48, Folder 857)
  - Box 7, folder 140 (Box 48, Folder 858)
  - Box 7, folder 142 (Box 48, Folder 859)
  - Box 7, folder 143 (Box 48, Folder 860)
  - Box 7, folders 144-145 (Box 48, Folder 861-862)
  - Box 7, folder 150 (Box 48, Folder 863)
  - Box 7, folder 151 (Box 48, Folder 864)
  - Box 7, folder 154 (Box 48, Folder 865)
  - Box 7, folder 155 (Box 48, Folder 866)
  - Box 7, folder 160 (Box 48, Folder 867)
  - Box 7, folder 162 (Box 48, Folder 868)
  - Box 7, folder 165 (Box 48, Folder 869)
  - Box 8, folder 166 (Box 49, Folder 870)
  - Box 8, folder 179 (Box 49, Folder 871)
  - Box 8, folder 183 (Box 49, Folder 872)
  - Box 11, folders 209-215 (Box 49, Folder 873-875)
  - Box 12, folder 220 (Box 49, Folder 875a)
  - Box 12, folder 223 (Box 49, Folder 875b)
  - Box 18, folder 305 (Box 50, Folder 876)
  - Box 23, folder 373 (Box 50, Folder 877)
  - Box 34, folder 602 (Box 50, Folder 878)
  - Box 4, folder 90 (Box 51, Folder 879-904)
  - Empty folder (Box 51, Folder 905)
  - Box 4, folder 90 (Box 52, Folder 906-913)
  - Box 4, folders 915-929 (Box 52, Folder 914-932)
  - Box 4, folders 915-929 (Box 53, Folder 933-938)
  - Box 11, folders 209-215 (Box 53, Folder 939-955)
  - Box 23, folder 373 (Box 54, Folder 956-963)
  - Box 23, folder 378 (Box 54, Folder 964-965)
  - Box 23, folder 388 (Box 54, Folder 966)
  - Box 28, folder 447 (Box 54, Folder 967-979)
  - Box 34, folder 603 (Box 54, Folder 980)
  - Box 6, folder 117 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 981)
  - Box 6, folder 118 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 982)
  - Box 7, folder 153 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 983)
  - Box 12, folders 221-222 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 984-985)
  - Box 15, folders 278-279 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 986)
  - Box 16, folder 290 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 987)
  - Box 31, folder 502 (Box 55 (Oversize), Folder 988)
  - Box 4, folders 93-95 (Box cs, Folder 989-994)
  - Box 6, folders 111-114 (Box cs, Folder 995-1003)
  - Box 11, folder 216 (Box cs, Folder 1004)
  - Box 12, folder 223 (Box cs, Folder 1005)
  - Box 15, folder 270 (Box cs, Folder 1006-1008)
- Restricted Fragile Art Objects, 0.2' (1 box)
  - Box 6, folder 130 (Box 56, Folder 1009)
  - Box 6, folder 131 (Box 56, Folder 1010)
  - Box 30, folder 475 (Box art, Folder 1011)
- 2009 Acquisition, 1920-1986; Series VI
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence regarding the California Historical Society's Utopian Studies Collection, 1955-1986; 2 (Box 57, Folder 1012-1013)
    - Correspondence regarding the Oakland Museum's Utopia Project and the California Historical Society, 1971-1976; 2 (Box 57, Folder 1014-1015)
  - Research Material and Publications
    - New World Utopias research, 1920, 1974, 1984-1985 (Box 57, Folder 1016)
    - New World Utopias carbon copies (oversize), undated (Box 58, Folder 1017)
    - American Utopias research material: The East Village Other newspaper and unidentified San Francisco newspapers (oversize), 1966, undated (Box 58, Folder 1018)